Guide to the Virginia deMorat Smith Scheetz papers, 1941-1968, 1947-1968 (bulk)
Scheetz, Virginia deMorat Smith papers, 1941-1968, 1947-1968 (bulk)
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Virginia deMorat Smith Scheetz papers, 1941-1968, 1947-1968 (bulk)
21-18-1108
Virginia deMorat Smith Scheetz.
3.2 cubic ft.
Class notes, newsletters, promotional material, newspaper clippings, photographs, tapes, correspondence, minutes, balance sheets, a yearbook, and other miscellaneous papers.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes notes from classes in ornithology, floriculture, and conservation; Cornell University Laboratory of Ornithology newsletter, printed and promotional material, newspaper clippings, photographs, two tapes of bird calls by Myles North, and correspondence, minutes, and balance sheets of the Advisory Council; notes and correspondence regarding Scheetz' speeches; correspondence, minutes, newsletter, and yearbook of the Pennsylvania Horticultural Society; material on the Garden Club of America and the Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania; and other correspondence, printed material, and miscellaneous papers of Virginia Scheetz.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Virginia Scheetz was the wife of Cornell University Trustee Francis Harley Scheetz. She took ornithology courses from Arthur A. Allen and Elsa G. Allen in the summers of 1947, 1948, 1950, and 1952, and later spoke on ornithology at schools, garden clubs, and church groups. Her other interests included horticulture and floriculture.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Two interests of Mrs. Virginia deMorat Smith Scheetz were ornithology and horticulture, and her papers are divided into these two basic categories.
The wife of a Cornell University trustee, Francis Harley Scheetz, Jr., Mrs. Scheetz came to Cornell in the summers of 1947, 1948, 1950, and 1952, taking courses in ornithology with Dr. Arthur A. Allen and his wife Elsa G. Allen and forming lasting friendships not only with the Allens but with others connected with the Laboratory of Ornithology, as is reflected in the correspondence. These courses so excited Mrs. Scheetz' interest in ornithology that she in turn influenced others with her enthusiasm, giving talks on ornithology to organizations such as schools, garden clubs, and church groups, primarily in the Northeast area.
Her class notes and notebooks while Dr. Allen's student, plus class notes from two other courses, one in floriculture and one in conservation, are of special interest in this collection. Correspondence with Laboratory of Ornithology personalities such as Arthur and Elsa Allen, Sally Hoyt (Spofford), Peter Paul Kellogg, O.S. Pettingill, Charles Sibley, Myles North, Gustav Swanson, and Cornell administrators Dale R. Corson and Arthur Peterson constitute another area worthy of note, since Mrs. Scheetz served as a member of the Advisory Council, later Administrative Board, of the Laboratory of Ornithology during the period 1956 to 1960 and 1961 to 1964.
The minutes of the meetings of the aforementioned Advisory Council, the Laboratory's newsletter, of which Mrs. Scheetz was editor for five years, and general material from Cornell's Laboratory of Ornithology, such as promotional handouts for the Lab and its various sound and photography projects, articles about the Laboratory and by staff members, news clippings, photographs, two tapes of bird calls by Myles North, and general correspondence concerning speech arrangements and reflecting her influence on others concerning ornithology, rounds out this part of the collection.
Also included in this section on ornithology are the notes on 3" by 5" cards that Mrs. Scheetz used for her speeches during the years 1948 to 1968. They merit special attention, as they give not only an outline of the speech, but indicate where and when the speech was given and include remarks on slides and records used. These slides and records were products of the Laboratory of Ornithology.
The latter part of the collection is devoted to Mrs. Scheetz' horticultural interests: material from the Pennsylvania Horticultural Society, Garden Club of America, and Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania. This material includes correspondence, minutes of the Executive Board meetings of the Pennsylvania Horticultural Society on which Mrs. Scheetz served, newsletters, yearbooks, and various pieces of literature on House and Garden tours, Garden Club shows, and other activities of these groups in which Mrs. Scheetz participated.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Scheetz, Virginia deMorat Smith.; Allen, Arthur A. (Arthur Augustus), 1885-1964.; Allen, Elsa Guerdrum, 1888-1969.; North, Myles E. W.; Cornell University. Laboratory of Ornithology.; Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania.; Garden Club of America.; Pennsylvania Horticultural Society.
Subjects:
Floriculture.; Horticulture.; Ornithology.; Women ornithologists.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Restricted to permission of the Archivist.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Ornithology
Class notes
Box 1
Laboratory of Ornithology
Boxes 2-4
Mrs. Scheetz' speeches
Boxes 5-6
General
Box 7
Series II. Horticulture
Pennsylvania Horticultural Society
Boxes 7-8
Garden Clubs
Box 8
General
Box 8
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Ornithology
  - Class notes
    - Ornithology A9, Summer 1947, Dr. Allen, Autograph notes, grades (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Special Problems in Ornithology under Dr. Arthur A. Allen, July 7-Aug. 14, 1948, Autograph notes (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - History and Literature of Ornithology, Dr. E.A. Allen, 1948, Autograph notes (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Complete Bibliography of Books and partial one of articles edited ... Dr. Elliott Cones, Autograph notes (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Special Problems in Ornithology under Dr. Arthur A. Allen, July 5-Aug. 12, 1950, Autograph notes (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Special Problems in Ornithology: Short Birds, July 7-29, 1952, Autograph notes, 3x5 notes (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Floriculture, 1947, Autograph notes (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Conservation, Prof. Oliver Hewitt, 1950, Autograph notes (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Ornithology laboratory notebook, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Ornithology laboratory notebook, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Laboratory of Ornithology
    - Advisory Council/Administrative Board
      - Advisory Council correspondence, 1947-1950, Arthur A. Allen, Elsa G. Allen (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Advisory Council correspondence, 1951-1955, Arthur A. Allen, Charles G. Sibley, Deane W. Malott (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Advisory Council correspondence, 1954-1955, Sapsucker Woods, Arthur A. Allen (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Advisory Council correspondence, 1956, Sapsucker Woods, scientific collecting, Arthur A. Allen, Sally Hoyt (Mrs. Southgate), Charles G. Sibley (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Advisory Council correspondence, 1957, Photographs, Arthur A. Allen, Elsa Allen, Sally Hoyt, Peter Paul Kellogg, Arthur H. Peterson (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Advisory Council correspondence, 1958, Arthur A. Allen, Sally Hoyt, Peter Paul Kellogg, Arthur H. Peterson, Charles G. Sibley (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Advisory Council correspondence, 1959-1960, Arthur A. Allen, Elsa Allen, Sally Hoyt, Peter Paul Kellogg, Myles North, Gustav Swanson (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Advisory Council correspondence, 1961-1962, Arthur A. Allen, Elsa Allen, Sally Hoyt, Peter Paul Kellogg, Myles North (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Advisory Council correspondence, 1963, Sally Hoyt, Myles North (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Advisory Council correspondence, 1964, Elsa Allen, Dale R. Corson, Sally Hoyt, Myles North, O.S. Pettingill, Jr. (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Advisory Council correspondence, 1965, Elsa Allen, Sally Hoyt, Douglas A. Lancaster (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Advisory Council correspondence, 1966-1968, Elsa Allen, O.S. Pettingill, Jr. (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Advisory Council correspondence, n.d., Elsa Allen, Charles Sibley, Jack Syme (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - "Friends through Birds," correspondence, 1947-1963, Christmas cards, Arthur A. Allen, Byrl and Paul Kellogg, Percival Dodge (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Advisory Council, minutes of meetings, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Advisory Council, minutes of meetings, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Advisory Council, minutes of meetings, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Advisory Council, minutes of meetings, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Advisory Council, minutes of meetings, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Advisory Council, minutes of meetings, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Advisory Council, minutes of meetings, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - David Allen and Bird Photo's Inc., correspondence, reports, 1964, Bird photography, O.S. Pettingill, Jr., David G. Allen (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Advisory Council, minutes of meetings, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Advisory Council, minutes of meetings, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Administrative Board reports and financial statements, 1963-1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Newsletter
      - Advisory Council (autograph notes), 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Newsletter, 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Newsletter, 1962-1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - General
      - Promotional material, 1960, 1963, 1968, Advertisements (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Promotional material, 1958, Photographs, slides (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Printed matter, articles, 1949-1963 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Newspaper articles, 1948-1965 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Photographs, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Miscellaneous: invitation, program, lists, 1957, 1962, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Tapes recordings of bird calls (2 reels), 1961, 1963, Myles North (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Mrs. Scheetz' speeches
    - Correspondence, speech arrangements, 1948, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, speech arrangements, 1953, Century Club, Scranton, Penna.; Garden Club of Bala Cynwyd (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, speech arrangements, 1954, Women's Club of Ardmore, Penna.; Penna. School of Horticulture (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, speech arrangements, 1955, Raymond J. Middleton, Bird Club of Philadelphia, Penna. Society of the Colonial Dames of America (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, speech arrangements, 1956, Landsdowne Garden Club (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, speech arrangements, 1957, Emmaus Garden Club, Norwood Horticultural Society (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, speech arrangements, 1958, Cosmopolitan Club of Philadelphia, York Society of Farm Women (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, speech arrangements, 1959, Hanover Garden Club (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, speech arrangements, 1960, Garden Club of Englewood, Therson Civic Association, Morristown Garden Club (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, speech arrangements, 1961, Garden Club of New York (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, speech arrangements, 1962, New York Botanical Garden (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, speech arrangements, 1963-1964, Delaware Federation of Garden Clubs (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, speech arrangements, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - General
    - Correspondence, Arizona, 1960-1965 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Arizona, 1964, Field cards, autograph check list, brochures, newsletter (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, Wyoming, 1965-1967, Brochure, field cards (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Wyoming, manual, 1939, Otto McCreary (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1955, 1967, Field cards, membership cards, notes, brochure, bird cards (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Series II. Horticulture
  - Pennsylvania Horticultural Society
    - Correspondence, 1952, 1956-1964 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1965, Ernesta D. Bulford (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Minutes of meetings, 1959-1961 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Minutes of meetings, 1962-1964 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Medal: correspondence, citations, 1941, 1953, 1956, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Newsletters, 1962, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Yearbooks, 1942, 1957-1960, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Other publications, brochures, printed material, 1957-1964 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Other printed material (articles, brochures), Independence Park, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Garden Clubs
    - The Garden Club of America: Wissahicken Garden Club: Correspondence, 1961-1963, Percival Dodge (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - The Garden Club of America: pamphlet, bulletin, 1952-1966, Percival Dodge (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Chart and photos, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania: correspondence, autograph report, records, 1948-1953 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania: lists, brochures, 1952, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Garden Club Federation of Pennsylvania: "Home and Garden Tour": correspondence, brochure, article, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - General
    - Articles, pamphlets, 1943, 1951, 1954, 1958, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Membership cards, pamphlets, postcards, 1967-1968 (Box 8, Folder 13)